Finding Aid for William Muschenheim papers 1923-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- University of Michigan Teaching Career 1951-1989
  Muschenheim arrived at the University of Michigan as a visiting professor in 1950, but stayed after one semester to become professor of architecture in the same year. Material in the University of Michigan Teaching Career, College of Architecture and Design Series (1.5 linear feet, 1951-1989) sheds light on the level of enthusiasm and depth of thinking he brought to teaching. Close inspection of the series will reveal some of the ways his integrated and universal approach to life and work manifested itself in the academic world. Essentially comprised of course materials -- syllabi, lecture notes, handouts, reading lists, and exam questions, a large portion (.75 linear ft.) contains student papers from Architecture 523, "Theory and Philosophy in Architecture," arranged topically. Students in this class analyzed aspects of philosophical and intellectual attitudes that prevailed in various time periods and in various parts of the world, writing papers that described "aspects which have universal validity in providing guidance towards the solution of contemporary architectural problems." [Architecture 523, Box, Muschenheim Papers] The other course most fully documented is Architecture 82, "History of Design." Its emphasis was on the recognition of the historic role of the designer to "crystallize in visual symbols what poets and philosophers were crystallizing verbally." The purpose, however, was "to bring bearing on a more complete evaluation of the contemporary scene...to become clearer as to what led up to the present circumstances." [Architecture 82, Box, Muschenheim Papers] Additional material in the series includes the doctoral work of Maggi Jonsson, leading Icelandic architect, committee participation (including the Theater Building Committee for the University of Michigan's Power Center) and correspondence.
  - College of Architecture and Design Faculty Minutes 1958-1966, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Committees 1958-1961, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Committee: University Theater Building, 1964-67, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Faculty, University of Michigan 1958-1982, 1960-1961, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Incoming 1951-1980 (Box 1)
    - Outgoing 1935, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Reference Letters 1935-1961 (Box 1)
  - Course Materials
    - History of Design 82, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Architecture 90 (Box 1)
    - Architecture 110 (Box 1)
    - Architecture 322 (Box 1)
    - Architecture 412 (Box 1)
    - Architecture 422 (Box 1)
    - Architecture 492 (Box 1)
    - Architecture 512 (Box 1)
    - Architecture 522 (Box 1)
    - Architecture 523 Ideas and Architecture / Student Papers (Box 2)
      - General, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Ancient
        - Egypt (Box 2)
        - Hellenistic Greece and Rome (Box 2)
      - Middle Ages
        - Early Christian and Byzantine (Box 2)
        - Romanesque (Box 2)
        - Gothic and Scholasticism (Box 2)
      - Renaissance and Baroque
        - Baroque and Age of Reason (Box 2)
        - Renaissance and Reformation (Box 2)
      - Islam and Far East
        - Islamic (Box 2)
        - China (Box 2)
        - India (Box 2)
        - Japan (Box 2)
      - Modern
        - Neo-Classicism and Enlightenment (Box 2)
        - Romanticism (Box 2)
        - Utilitarianism (Box 2)
        - Modern (Box 2)
        - Twentieth Century Technology, Industry (Box 2)
    - Architecture 562 (Box 2)
    - Architecture 719
      - Maggi Jonsson (Box 2)
    - Bibliography (Box 2)
    - Dennis Holloway, Solar Architecture (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Publications and Research 1930-1989
  Very strong and important to the collection is the Publications and Research Series (4.5 linear feet; 1930-1989). This series offers researchers the opportunity to review Muschenheim's thinking, projects, and research through his own published work and in the numerous articles written about his accomplishments that were published around the world in important journals and magazines. Material covers the full range of his career. Articles about Muschenheim are arranged chronologically by decade from the 1930s through the 1980s, followed by articles related to competitions and exhibition catalogs. Publications by Muschenheim include one example of PLUS the revolutionary journal he helped found in the mid-thirties that was devoted to modern architecture; many pieces documenting his research in comparative architectural curricula; and papers regarding the production of Elements of the Art of Architecture and Why Architecture. The color plates developed for Why Architecture along with his commentary on historic applications, have particular significance because of Mushenheim's early and ongoing interest in the use of color and his unique ability to utilize it as an intrinsic architectural element.
  - About Muschenheim and His Work
    - 1930s
      - Peter Behrens and His Academic Master School Adolf Luser Edition: Vienna, Berlin, Leipzig, 1930 (Box 3)
      - "Peter Behrens Architect and Teacher," The Architectural Forum, May 1930 (Box 3)
      - " Peter Behrens Architect and Teacher," Architectural Digest, May 1930 (Box 3)
      - "Designs by William Muschenheim," Architectural Record, October 1930 (Box 3)
      - "The New School for Social Research," Architectural Record, February 1931 (Box 3)
      - "Umbau Eines Wohnhauses Auf Long Island," Moderne Bauformen, September 1932 (Box 3)
      - "Penthouse International Style," Arts and Decoration, January 1934 (Box 3)
      - "Portfolio: Modernization and Alteration," The Architectural Record, June 1934 (Box 3)
      - "Design Two: Unit Plan, One Story Week-end House Inland or Near Bay," Arts and Decoration, July 1934 (Box 3)
      - "Portfolio of Interior Architecture," Arts and Decoration, October 1934 (Box 3)
      - "A Penthouse Apartment in New York City," Architectural Record, November 1934 (Box 3)
      - "Selected Review of the World's Best Modern," Arts and Decoration, January 1935 (Box 3)
      - "Wohnungsausstattung in USA," Innen-Dekoration, April 1935 (Box 3)
      - "The House that Works," Fortune, October 1935 (Box 13)
        (missing p. 96 with photograph of Muschenheim house)
      - "The Apartment Interior," Architectural Record, October 1936 (Box 3)
      - "Portfolio of Small Houses and Apartment Buildings," Architectural Record, October 1936 (Box 3)
      - New York State World's Fair Guide, New York: Exposition Publications Inc., 1939 (Box 3)
    - 1940s
      - "Dos Decoraciones Realizadas En Nueva York," Casa Y Jardines, Enero 1941 (Box 3)
      - "Accent on Space," Architectural Record, July 1942 (Box 3)
      - "Planned for Site and Sunlight," Architectural Record, March 1943 (Box 3)
      - Reports of the Home of Tomorrow Contest (4), McCall Corporation 1944 (Box 3)
    - 1950s
      - "The Architect's Home in Ann Arbor," International Asbestos Cement Review (AC 3), July 1956 (Box 3)
      - "Detroit Chapter Honor Awards," Monthly Bulletin, November 1959 (Box 3)
    - 1960s
      - Book Announcement Technology Review, July 1965 (Box 3)
    - 1970s
      - "Rejected Architects," Oppositions, 1974 (Box 3)
    - 1980s
      - "Europe and Modernism's First Years: An American Witness," CRIT 19: The Architectural Student Journal, Winter 1987 (Box 3)
    - Competitions
      - "New York World's Fair," Pencil Points, December 1936 (Box 3)
      - "Middle East Technical University," Progressive Architecture, March 1960 (Box 3)
    - Exhibitions
      - Modern Architecture at the New School of Social Research (Box 3)
      - Catalogue of Projects by Graduates from the Behrens Master School of Architecture at the Academy of Fine Arts in Vienna and Photographs of Professor Behren's Work, Brooklyn Museum, April 21, 1930-May 26, 1930 (Box 3)
      - Long Island Modern: The First Generation of Modern Architecture on Long Island, 1928-1960, 1987 (Box 3)
      - Beux Arch '89 / The Architectural Exposition of the Hamptons, July 1989 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous News Clippings and Articles, 193?-1983 (Box 3)
    - "The House that Works," Fortune, October 1935 (Box 13)
  - By Muschenheim
    - "Color Studies in Remodeling," Architectural Record, October 1931 (Box 3)
    - PLUS [Supplement to Architectural Forum], 1939 (Box 3)
    - Comparative Architectural Curricula Publications
      - "Report Made at Faculty Meeting," September 25, 1958 (Box 3)
      - Architectural Education, 1959 (Box 3)
      - "A Report on European Schools of Architecture," American Institute of Architects Journal, July 1959 (Box 3)
      - A Comparative Curricula of a Number of Representative Schools of Architecture in Western Europe, December 1959 (Box 3)
      - "Detroit Chapter, A.I.A.," Monthly Bulletin, Michigan Society of Architects, June 1960 (Box 3)
      - "Curricula in Schools of Architecture: A Directory," Journal of Architectural Education, March 1964 (Box 3)
      - "Curricula in Schools of Architecture: A Directory," American Institute of Architecture Journal, March 1964 (Box 3)
      - "Committee on International Relations," Annual Report of the Board (ACSA), 1966 (Box 3)
      - NCARB Meeting [National Council of Architectural Review Boards], October 1-2, 1967 (Box 3)
      - World Tour Itinerary and Costs 1972 (Box 3)
      - Architectural Curricula in Foreign Countries: A Report, 1973 (Box 3)
      - Charts: Originals (Box 3)
      - Correspondence (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous Papers (Box 3)
    - Architecture Bibliography, January 1961 (Box 3)
    - Elements of the Art of Architecture, Viking Press, 1964
      - Arnold W. Brunner Scholarship (Box 4)
      - Autographed copy, "To Lisa" (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Credits: Addresses (Box 4)
      - Credits: Fees and Permissions, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Manuscript (Box 4)
      - Manuscript Introduction (Box 4)
      - Michigan National Architect (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
      - New York Trips 1961, 1962, 1963 (Box 4)
      - Photographs (Box 4)
      - Planning (Box 4)
      - Proofs (Box 4)
      - Publicity, Reviews (Box 4)
      - Rackham Grant (Box 4)
      - Reference Material, Addresses (Box 4)
    - Sabbatical 1964
      - Application, Rackham School of Graduate Studies (Box 4)
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - Itinerary etc. (Box 4)
      - Travel Diary (Box 4)
      - Vouchers, Clippings, Notes (Box 4)
    - Why Architecture, Karoma Publishers Inc., 1980
      - Accounting (Box 4)
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - Drafts of Manuscript, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Layout Notes (Box 4)
      - Legal (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous Plates and Photographs (Box 4)
      - Negatives of Plates (Box 4)
      - Negatives of Alternated Plates (Box 5)
      - Notes and Miscellaneous (Box 5)
      - Printed Collected Material (Box 5)
      - Promotion and Mailing Lists (Box 5)
      - Reviews and Commentaries (Box 5)
      - Studies (Box 5)
      - Xerox of Manuscript April 8, 1976 (Box 5)
      - Color Plates (Page Layouts)
        - Classicism (Box 5)
        - Medieval (Box 5)
        - Baroque (Box 5)
        - Pre-Columbian (Box 5)
        - Japan (Box 5)
        - Thailand and Burma (Box 5)
        - Ancient India (Box 6)
        - Mogul India (Box 6)
        - India (Box 6)
        - Modern Commercial (Box 6)
        - Modern Civic (Box 6)
        - Signatures and Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - "A Review of Some of the Particular Design Components Conducive to Satisfying Architectural Realization," Western Michigan Chapter of American Institute of Architects, 1984 (Box 7)
    - "E.A. Plischke zum 80.Geburtstag," Juni 1983 (Box 7)
    - Collected Materials
      - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
      - Astor Hotel and Times Square (Box 7)
      - Travel (Box 7)
    - Reference Data
      - General (Box 7)
      - Overseas (Box 7)
      - Theater Design (Box 7)
      - United States (Box 7)
      - Washington D.C. (Box 7)
- Work Files 1930-1989
  For researchers interested in architectural drawings and material documenting architectural projects, the Project Files series (2.5 linear feet and 7 flat drawers) and a parallel series of oversized Original Drawings and Prints will be of primary importance. The Project Files series is comprised of records such as correspondence, notes, reports and accounting material, as well as original drawings and prints, and is arranged by work number as assigned by Muschenheim. The Bentley Library collection has project files beginning with #132, the William Muschenheim House, 1952-53 (except for one sketch of the Anita Zahn house, #112, and one rendering of the William J. Murphy House, #113) and running through #193, Otis Taylor Consultation. The series does not include documentation for the following projects: #154-161; 164-168, 170-171; 173-174; 179-180; and 182.
  Projects with the most complete sets of drawings include #132, William Muschenheim House; #133, Alterations to the Burton Harrison Residence; #135, Don E. Rutledge House; and #146 Phi Epsilon Pi Fraternity House. Also of note are drawings produced for the International Headquarters and Conference Center, Vienna, Austria, #162, an international competition. A "Supplemental Guide" to projects by work number begins on page 23, and a list of projects dated by Mushenheim is attached to this finding aid. The original dividers used by Muschenheim in his filing system are in box 14. Dividers with substantial information written on them were photocopied onto acid-free paper and placed with related drawings or related folders. Researchers considering Muschenheim's work with color will find the following projects which include color studies particularly interesting: Muschenheim House, #132; Harrison House, #133; Rutledge House, #135; International Organization Headquarters Competition, #162; and the East Hampton Air Terminal (unnumbered).
  - #132 William Muschenheim: House 1952-1988
    - Brochures (Box 7)
    - Accounting, Contracts (Box 7)
    - Construction Data, Estimates (Box 7)
    - Correspondence (Box 7)
    - Description of Original Working Drawings (Box 7)
    - Financial Records, Purchases (Box 7)
    - Notes, Computations (Box 7)
    - Original Drawings, Details, pencil on tracing paper (Box 7)
    - Purchases (Box 7)
    - Progress Reports (Box 7)
    - Specifications (Box 7)
  - #133 Burton Harrison: Alterations to Residence and Additions 1955-1984
    - Accounting, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Catalogues (Box 7)
    - Color (Box 7)
    - Construction Data, Estimates, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Correspondence (Box 7)
    - Legal (Box 7)
    - Notes, Memos (Box 7)
    - Original Drawings, Miscellaneous, pencil and red pencil on Xerox prints; pencil on vellum and tracing paper (Box 7)
    - Original Working Drawings 27-34, 36-38,41-50, 53, 55-64, 2 folders pencil and orange pencil on tracing paper and vellum; colored pencil on Xerox prints (Box 7)
    - Surveys (Box 7)
  - #134 Martin Bernstein: Alterations to Residence 1955 (Box 7)
  - #135 Don H. Rutledge: House 1957
    - Accounting (Box 7)
    - Catalogs and Samples (Box 7)
    - Correspondence (Box 7)
    - Estimates (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
    - Notes and Memos (Box 7)
    - Specifications (Box 7)
    - Superintendence Reports (Box 7)
    - Window Schedule, Notes (Box 7)
  - #136 Museum of Art, University of Michigan: Main Stair, Platforms and Exhibition Space 1957
    - Catalogs (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, Accounting (Box 8)
    - Lighting (Box 8)
    - Preliminary Estimates (Box 8)
    - Preliminaries and Photo (Box 8)
    - Calculations and Notes (Box 8)
    - Specifications (Box 8)
  - #137 G. Bruce McCaleb: Alterations to Residence 1957, includes original working drawings, pencil on tracing paper (Box 8)
  - #138 Ankers International Competition, Middle East Technical University: Building for School of Administrative Sciences 1960 (Box 8)
  - #139 F.D.R. Memorial Competition: Memorial in Washington [Franklin Delano Roosevelt] 1961 (Box 8)
  - #140 Joseph Blatt: Alterations to Residence [Consultation] 1960 (Box 8)
  - #141 Harry Lieberman: Designs for Development Houses 1960 (Box 8)
  - #143 A. Benjamin Handler: Alterations to Residence 1961 (Box 8)
    (includes original working drawing, pencil and yellow pencil on tracing paper)
  - #145 Robert E. Schwartz: Consultations-Church, Shopping Center 1963 (Box 8)
  - #146 Phi Epsilon Pi Fraternity House: Alterations and Annex 1966
    - Accounting, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Catalogs (Box 8)
    - Certificates (Box 8)
    - Colors (Box 8)
    - Correspondence (Box 8)
    - Estimates (Box 8)
    - Kitchen (Box 8)
    - Legal (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Notes and Memos (Box 8)
    - Orders (Box 8)
    - Original Drawings, Details, 1-8 through 30-8, pencil on tracing paper (Box 8)
    - Original Drawings, Studies, pencil on tracing paper (Box 8)
    - Photographs and Plans of Original (Box 8)
    - Plans of Existing House (Box 8)
    - Prints, Details, bluelines and blacklines (Box 8)
    - Proposal (Box 8)
    - Record of Issuance of Drawings and Specs (Box 8)
    - Reports (Box 8)
    - Samples (Box 8)
    - Specifications (Box 8)
    - Superintendence Reports (Box 8)
  - #147 Claude A. Eggersten: Addition to Residence 1966 (Box 8)
  - #149 Richard Stoll: Consultation re: Residence 1966 (Box 8)
  - #150 Alpha Ki Delta Sorority: Consultations re: Building 1957 (Box 8)
  - #152 Sleepy Hollow Cemetery: Gravestone, Lisa Muschenheim 1967, includes original sketches and drawings, pencil on tracing paper, and photographs (Box 8)
  - #153 Emile Voelcker: Addition to Residence 1967, includes original drawings, pencil and colored pencil on tracing paper (Box 8)
  - #157 Mr. and Mrs. Ned Flanders: Alterations to Residence 1968 (Box 8)
  - #162 International Organization Headquarters and Conference Center, Vienna, Austria: International Competition 1969 (Box 8)
  - #163 Mr. and Mrs. Robert Knauss: Week-End House 1970
    - Catalogs (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Estimates, Contracts (Box 8)
    - Sketches, pencil and water color on graph paper (Box 8)
    - Specifications (Box 8)
  - #169 Mr. Sabaliunas: Alteration to Residence [Consultation] 1969, includes original sketches, marker on graph paper (Box 8)
  - #172 Joseph T.A. Lee: Market Arbor "A" Center 1970 (Box 9)
  - #176 Rockresorts: Lobby-Board Room 1971 (Box 9)
  - #177 Channing Jacques: Addition to Cottage 1971, includes original drawings, pencil on tracing paper; pencil and blue ink on tracing paper (Box 9)
  - #178 A.B. Handler: Addition to House 1972 (Box 9)
  - #181 City of Grand Rapids Museum: Re: Addition to Old Federal Building 1974 (Box 9)
  - #183 Dr. Helen Gay: Addition to House 1976
    - Accounting, Prints, Miscellaneous (Box 9)
    - Color Schedule (Box 9)
  - #184 Ara G. Paul: Addition and Alterations to House 1977, 1987
    - Accounting, Legal (Box 9)
    - Calculations, Surveys, Notes (Box 9)
    - Catalogs (Box 9)
    - Color Studies, paint and cut paper on Xerox prints (Box 9)
    - Original Working Drawings, 1-15; 17 1977, pencil on tracing paper and vellum (Box 9)
    - Original Working Drawings, 19-21, pencil on tracing paper and vellum (Box 9)
  - #186 Hermann Hermannsson: House 1980
    - Accounting, Legal (Box 9)
    - Catalogs (Box 9)
    - Surveys (Box 9)
  - #187 Silas Woods: House 1980, 1985
    - Accounting (Box 9)
    - Original Sketches, blue marker on tracing paper; colored pencil on tracing paper and yellow note paper (Box 9)
  - #188 J.E. Keith Smith: Railing and Approach to Residence 1983 (Box 9)
  - #189 Peter Meister: Alteration to Residence 1985, includes original working drawing, pencil and red ink on tracing paper (Box 9)
  - #190 Robert Cole: Consultation 1987 (Box 9)
  - #191Mr. and Mrs Dozauer: Residence Alterations 1987
    - Original Drawings, Color Studies, pencil and colored pencil on tracing paper; pencil on notebook paper (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - #193 Otis Taylor: Consultation 1988
    - Catalogs, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous Folder of Unidentified Sketches and Calculations (Box 9)
  - Notes: Engineering Mechanics War Training Course, 1934-1936, 3 folders contents of 2 notebooks (Box 9)
  - Project Dividers (Box 14)
    (Dividers which were removed from Project Files. Those with significant written information were photocopied and are filed with relevant drawings)
- Photographs and Accompanying Material
  The only series in the collection (except journal and magazine articles in the Publications and Research Series), which contain substantial material related to Muschenheim's career prior to arrival in Michigan are the Photographs and Accompanying Material (3.25 linear feet, 1930-198?) and the Presentation Boards (1.75 linear feet and 1 flat drawer, 1930-1961).
  Photographs are arranged alphabetically by project, close to the order in which they arrived at the library as filed by Muschenheim; work numbers were added when known. "Accompanying Material" refers to a variety of documents Muschenheim occasionally filed with the photographs, ranging from copies of architectural drawings to sketches and clippings. Most of the images of earlier work are black and white prints, most of those after 1960 are color snapshots or color slides, and many of the files include original negatives. The series contains black and white photographs that were published in many parts of the world -- Muschenheim's school projects and projects undertaken at the Hotel Astor and on Hampton Bays, Long Island, for example. Many of the residences he designed and apartments he remodeled are also visually documented, including the home he built for his family in Ann Arbor in 1952. A portion of the series is comprised of photographs depicting projects Muschenheim designed early in his career (material documenting these projects--1 through 130--are mainly held at the Avery Library, Columbia University.
  - Astor (#39)
    - Ballroom Old and New (Box 10)
    - Bar and Cafe (Box 10)
    - Belvedere and Open Roof (Box 10)
    - Carl and Linda's Rooms (Box 10)
    - Eighth Floor Coat Rooms (Box 10)
    - Exterior Views New (Box 10)
    - Exterior Views Old (Box 10)
    - Grill Room (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
    - Reception Rooms (Box 10)
    - Old Restaurant Lobby (Box 10)
  - Burnett, Everit Residence (#90) (Box 10)
  - Competitions
    - Franklin D. Roosevelt (#139) (Box 10)
    - Middle East Technical University (#138) (Box 10)
    - Southern Rhodesia Parliament Building Competition (Box 10)
    - International Organization Headquarters and Conference Center (#162) (Box 10)
    - Wheaton College (#56) (Box 10)
  - De Liagre, Alfred House (#43), 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Drew, Wm. B.F. Apartment (#63) (Box 10)
  - Drew, Wm. B.F. House (#92) (Box 10)
  - Dunbar Apartment (#4) (Box 10)
  - Elliman, Douglas Apartments (#19) (Box 10)
  - Finch, Neil Apartment (#22) (Box 10)
  - Fletcher, Walter Apartment and House (#32, #69) (Box 10)
  - Freyl Haitain Art Center (#109) (Box 10)
  - Guggenheim Museum (#60, #102) (Box 10)
  - Gulden, Immo Apartment and House (#27) (Box 10)
  - Hampton Bays
    - Bath Houses on Dunes (Box 10)
    - Dr. Carl Muschenheim House (#31) (Box 10)
    - F.A. Muschenheim House Exterior (#3) (Box 10)
    - F.A. Muschenheim House Interior (#3) (Box 10)
    - Lighthouse (Box 10)
  - Hard House (#79) (Box 10)
  - Harlem Housing (Box 10)
  - Harrison,Burton House (#133), mainly color prints (Box 10)
  - Hawkes, A. W. House (#83) (Box 10)
  - Hermannson, Hermann (#186), color prints (Box 10)
  - International Congress of Modern Architecture, Baltimore Map (Box 10)
  - Mason, Terry Apartment (#111) (Box 10)
  - McPherson, Ross Dr. Office (#36) (Box 10)
  - M.I.T. Museum Project (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Architectural Photographs (Box 11)
    - Color Slides, Mixed (Box 11)